<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.2">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://thisisbalu.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/><link href="https://thisisbalu.github.io/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en"/><updated>2023-10-12T02:51:03+00:00</updated><id>https://thisisbalu.github.io/feed.xml</id><title type="html">blank</title><subtitle>A simple, whitespace theme for academics. Based on [*folio](https://github.com/bogoli/-folio) design. </subtitle><entry><title type="html">Different BRMS Tools in Market</title><link href="https://thisisbalu.github.io/different-brms-tools-market/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Different BRMS Tools in Market"/><published>2016-09-27T18:40:40+00:00</published><updated>2016-09-27T18:40:40+00:00</updated><id>https://thisisbalu.github.io/different-brms-tools-market</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://thisisbalu.github.io/different-brms-tools-market/"><![CDATA[<p>There are many vendors in the market who provide BRMS tools with a lot number of features with different pricing, standalone platforms, integrated suites and open source projects.</p> <p>Ranking of the BRMS tools those are available in the market it difficult. The competition between products revolves around the relationships with vendors or price competition according to the Forrester Analyst John Rymer. There are many factors on which a tool can be selected out of many factors. Some of them are cost, Platform support( Java/.net/cobol/etc), less dependence on IT department/Development, analytics and more complex event processing and many. Depending on the different requirements a tool will be selected.</p> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 480px)" srcset="/assets/img/blog/collage-1024x1024-480.webp"/> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 800px)" srcset="/assets/img/blog/collage-1024x1024-800.webp"/> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 1400px)" srcset="/assets/img/blog/collage-1024x1024-1400.webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/blog/collage-1024x1024.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="auto" height="auto" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> <p>Hence it is difficult to say that some tools are best and others are not. Here in this article, I have collected different BRMS tools from different vendors that serve the purpose according to their needs. I have categorized all the BRMS tools into three categories.</p> <blockquote> <p>The majority of the BRMS tools are java based, hence I categorized first one as Rich .Net Choice, second as Strongest Standalone Products and third as Open Source Tools.</p> </blockquote> <h2 id="rich-net-choice">Rich .Net Choice</h2> <p>As the majority of the BRMS tools available in the market are based on Java, .Net projects have a limited support. <a href="http://www.inrule.com/"> <em><strong>InRule BRMS tool</strong></em></a> provides exclusive support for the .NET background. Some of its products are</p> <ul> <li>InRule for Javascript</li> <li>InRule for Microsoft Azure(Cloud)</li> <li>InRule for Microsoft Dynamics CRM</li> </ul> <h2 id="strongest-standalone-products">Strongest Standalone Products</h2> <p>The tools categorized in this category have the strong set of features and the well-built components that support more business by minimizing IT maintenance costs.</p> <ul> <li>IBM’s BRMS, <a href="http://www-03.ibm.com/software/products/en/odm"><em><strong>Operations Decision Manager (ODM)</strong></em></a> which is previously called as Ilog JRules has a very rich feature set and relatively high price tag. IBM ODM suits more for those who look for analytics and complex event processing.</li> <li>FICO’s BRMS, <a href="http://www.fico.com/en/products/fico-blaze-advisor-decision-rules-management-system"><em><strong>Blaze Advisor</strong></em></a> also has the rich set of features with some decent pricing. As per some news, I gathered, some financial firms always favor FICO Blaze Advisor it seems.</li> <li>Progress’s BRMS, <a href="https://www.progress.com/corticon"><em><strong>Corticon</strong></em></a> have some well-built components at lower pricing than the ODM and Blaze.</li> <li>Recent days, there is a new tool introduced by Sparkling Logic called as the <a href="http://www.sparklinglogic.com/"><em><strong>SMARTS</strong></em></a> Decision Manager and PENCIL Decision Modeler. One of the interesting aspect of these tools is that Charles Forgy, inventor of RETE Algorithm is the main Advisor for SMARTS. Forgy developed a new generation of the RETE Algorithm called RETE-NT, which was claimed that it is 500 times faster than the original RETE Algorithm and 10 times faster than its predecessor RETE II. RETE-NT is the inference engine of the SMARTS product.</li> </ul> <h2 id="open-source-tools">Open Source Tools</h2> <p>Open source rule engines and rule management suites tend to be more developer focussed. Once the framework/architecture is built, these open source rule engines serve the purpose. But they lack in the advanced features provided by IBM, FICO, Progress, etc.</p> <ul> <li>Red hat’s JBOSS is the commercial distribution of the open-source BRMS tool <a href="http://www.drools.org/"><em><strong>DROOLS</strong></em></a>.</li> <li><a href="http://openrules.com/"><em><strong>OpenRules</strong></em></a> which is more simple and provides users to keep their Business rules in google docs or excel spreadsheets. This will be suitable for small business applications effectively.</li> <li><a href="http://www.jessrules.com/jess/index.shtml"><em><strong>JESS 7</strong></em></a>, is another open source rule engine which is suitable for the small scale business applications.</li> </ul> <p>These are the different BRMS tools available from different vendors in the current market. Happy Learning! Happy Exploring!!</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="BRMS"/><category term="brms"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[There are many vendors in the market who provide BRMS tools with a lot number of features with different pricing, standalone platforms, integrated suites and open source projects.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Applications of BRMS in the Real World</title><link href="https://thisisbalu.github.io/applications-brms-real-world/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Applications of BRMS in the Real World"/><published>2016-09-27T17:10:09+00:00</published><updated>2016-09-27T17:10:09+00:00</updated><id>https://thisisbalu.github.io/applications-brms-real-world</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://thisisbalu.github.io/applications-brms-real-world/"><![CDATA[<p>The main goal of BRMS is externalizing the Bussiness Condition Logic from the application code so that condition logics( technically called as rules) can be organized easily without disturbing the application. BRMS reduces the application developer dependency. A business user can directly edit business condition rules using BRMS. Some of the applications of brms are given below –</p> <h2 id="banking">Banking</h2> <p>loan origination, cross-sell offer management, payment fee calculations, credit risk decisions, etc.</p> <h2 id="capital-markets">Capital Markets</h2> <p>trade order validation, account onboarding, anti-money laundering compliance, general ledger data validation, etc.</p> <h2 id="healthcare-and-life-sciences">Healthcare and Life Sciences</h2> <p>clinical support, drug interaction assessment, clinical trails date validation, etc.</p> <h2 id="insurance">Insurance</h2> <p>policy underwriting, claims processing, risk rating, commission calculations, form attachments, etc.</p> <h2 id="manufacturing">Manufacturing</h2> <p>order configuration, validation, contract-based billing, order prioritization, etc.</p> <h2 id="public-sector">Public Sector</h2> <p>services entitlement and benefits calculation, tax-fraud assessment, homeland security screening, etc.</p> <h2 id="retail">Retail</h2> <p>online registration, loyalty programs, offers management, etc.</p> <h2 id="telecom">Telecom</h2> <p>offer configuration, service prioritization and assignment, cross-network billing, etc.</p> <h2 id="travel-and-transportation">Travel and Transportation</h2> <p>loyalty programs, contract based billing management, ticket pricing, etc.</p> <p>Happy Learning! Happy Exploring!!</p>]]></content><author><name>Bala Subramanyam Lanka</name></author><category term="BRMS"/><category term="brms"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[The main goal of BRMS is externalizing the Bussiness Condition Logic from the application code so that condition logics(technically called as rules) can be organized easily without disturbing the application.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Business Rule Management System (BRMS)</title><link href="https://thisisbalu.github.io/business-rule-management-system-brms/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Business Rule Management System (BRMS)"/><published>2016-09-27T16:26:10+00:00</published><updated>2016-09-27T16:26:10+00:00</updated><id>https://thisisbalu.github.io/business-rule-management-system-brms</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://thisisbalu.github.io/business-rule-management-system-brms/"><![CDATA[<p>Business Rule Management System (BRMS) is an integrated application development and execution platform that allows organizations to define, deploy and monitor and maintain the vast variety of Automated decisions used by operational systems. A BRMS allows decision logic to be extracted and managed separately from core application code, so that it can be easily understood, maintained and reused access the organization.</p> <p>The definition that is given in the above para is in technical terms. To define BRMS in the more general way –<em><strong>Externalizing the Business Condition Logic from the application code so that condition logics(technically called as rules) can be organized easily without disturbing the application.</strong></em> BRMS reduces the application developer dependency. A business user can directly edit business condition rules using BRMS.</p> <h2 id="components-of-business-rule-management-system">Components of Business Rule Management System</h2> <p>Business Rule Management System should include at least three primary components.<figure id="attachment_1494" aria-describedby="caption-attachment-1494" style="width: 840px" class="wp-caption aligncenter"></figure></p> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 480px)" srcset="/assets/img/blog/Components-of-BRMS-1024x897-480.webp"/> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 800px)" srcset="/assets/img/blog/Components-of-BRMS-1024x897-800.webp"/> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 1400px)" srcset="/assets/img/blog/Components-of-BRMS-1024x897-1400.webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/blog/Components-of-BRMS-1024x897.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="auto" height="auto" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> <h3 id="rule-repository">Rule Repository</h3> <p>A repository allowing rules to be externalized from core application code. The repository allows decision logic to be managed as an enterprise asset, making it easier to understand and update automated, operational decisions. This rule repository also helps in reusing the rule information across the application.</p> <h3 id="tools-for-both-technical-and-non-technical-users-to-define-and-manage-decision-logic-in-repository">Tools for both technical and non-technical users to define and manage decision logic in repository</h3> <p>These tools give the business function the ability to define rules that will guide the behavior of operational systems. These tools will facilitate collaboration between the technical and business on application maintenance and development.</p> <h3 id="runtime-engine">Runtime Engine</h3> <p>A runtime engine allowing systems to access and execute of rules in the engine will be based on specific execution algorithms.</p> <p>Happy Learning! Happy Exploring!!</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="BRMS"/><category term="brms"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Business Rule Management System (BRMS) is an integrated application development and execution platform that allows organizations to define, deploy and monitor and maintain the vast variety of Automated decisions used by operational systems.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">RetePlus Algorithm with Example – IBM ODM</title><link href="https://thisisbalu.github.io/reteplus-algorithm-example/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="RetePlus Algorithm with Example – IBM ODM"/><published>2016-06-04T20:00:23+00:00</published><updated>2016-06-04T20:00:23+00:00</updated><id>https://thisisbalu.github.io/reteplus-algorithm-example</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://thisisbalu.github.io/reteplus-algorithm-example/"><![CDATA[<p>RetePlus algorithm is one of the <a href="http://www.balasubramanyamlanka.com/rule-engine-execution-modes/">execution modes</a> in IBM ODM which is based on <a href="http://www.balasubramanyamlanka.com/rete-algorithm/">Rete algorithm</a>. It works based on working memory, agenda creation, supports negative patterns, object notification, and Logical Objects. Use RetePlus optimization techniques to improve performance through reduction of the number of rules and conditions, computation of the rules to run, and prioritization of the rule order.</p> <h2 id="working-of-reteplus-algorithm">Working of RetePlus Algorithm</h2> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 480px)" srcset="/assets/img/blog/Working-of-RetePlus-Algorithm-480.webp"/> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 800px)" srcset="/assets/img/blog/Working-of-RetePlus-Algorithm-800.webp"/> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 1400px)" srcset="/assets/img/blog/Working-of-RetePlus-Algorithm-1400.webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/blog/Working-of-RetePlus-Algorithm.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="auto" height="auto" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> <h3 id="step-1">Step 1</h3> <p>First, all the objects are loaded into the working memory. We call these objects as working memory objects.</p> <h3 id="step-2">Step 2</h3> <p>Rule Engine matches the rules with working memory objects.</p> <h3 id="step-3">Step 3</h3> <p>During this Pattern matching process, RetePlus algorithm creates a network based on semantic relationships between rule condition tests.</p> <h3 id="step-4">Step 4</h3> <p>If a rule got matched with the working memory objects, then the rule instance is created and added to the Agenda.</p> <h5 id="1-then-based-on-the-ordering-properties-agenda-selects-the-rule-instance-to-trigger">1. Then based on the Ordering properties, agenda selects the rule instance to trigger.</h5> <h5 id="2-the-rule-action-of-the-rule-gets-triggered">2. The rule action of the rule gets triggered.</h5> <h5 id="3-when-the-rules-are-firing-sometimes-there-comes-a-situation-where-the-working-memory-objects-get-updated-the-rule-action-can-modify-the-working-memory-objects-in-the-following-way">3. When the rules are firing, sometimes there comes a situation where the working memory objects get updated. The rule action can modify the working memory objects in the following way:</h5> <ul> <li>By adding an object to the working memory</li> <li>By removing an object from the working memory</li> <li>By modifying the attributes of an existing object.</li> </ul> <h5 id="4-whenever-the-working-memory-objects-get-updated-then-rule-engine-repeats-the-pattern-matching-process">4. Whenever the working memory objects get updated, then rule engine repeats the pattern matching process.</h5> <h5 id="5-it-reassesses-matches-after-each-rule-instance-is-run-and-modifies-the-data-as-a-possible-consequence-the-list-of-rule-instances-in-the-agenda-can-change">5. It reassesses matches after each rule instance is run and modifies the data. As a possible consequence, the list of rule instances in the agenda can change.</h5> <h5 id="6-thus-this-algorithm-is-incremental-and-data-driven">6. Thus, this algorithm is incremental and data-driven.</h5> <h5 id="7-this-algorithm-is-based-on-an-inference-process-that-the-sequential-and-fastpath-algorithms-do-not-support-in-ibm-odm">7. This algorithm is based on an inference process that the sequential and FastPath algorithms do not support in IBM ODM.</h5> <h5 id="8-this-algorithm-had-five-main-sections-they-are">8. This algorithm had five main sections. They are:</h5> <ul> <li>Working Memory</li> <li>Agenda</li> <li>Negative Patterns</li> <li>Object Notifications</li> <li>Network Operation</li> </ul> <h2 id="working-memory">Working Memory</h2> <p>Each Rule engine in the Decision server is paired with a working memory. The working memory contains all the objects contained in the associated IlrContext object (base class of all the execution contexts. Rules can be executed only within an execution context.). You can modify the working memory by adding a statement in the <em class="ph i">action part of a rule</em> or by using the Application Programming Interface (API).</p> <p>Thus, the rule engine is aware of the objects that are in the working memory and any objects that are linked to them. The rule engine can use only objects that are accessible from the working memory. Use the following methods to manage the working memory:</p> <ol> <li>insert</li> <li>retract</li> <li>update</li> <li>updateContext</li> <li>enumerateObjects</li> <li>getObjects</li> </ol> <p>Check <a href="https://www.ibm.com/support/knowledgecenter/en/SSQP76_8.5.1/com.ibm.odm.dserver.rules.ref.res/html/api/html/ilog/rules/engine/IlrContext.html?view=embed#insert(java.lang.Object)">here</a> for better understanding of the methods given above.</p> <h3 id="agenda">Agenda</h3> <p>The agenda is where <span class="keyword">Decision Server</span> stores the rules whose patterns are all matched. Any rule that enters the agenda is said to be instantiated, it becomes a rule instance<em class="ph i">. </em></p> <p class="p"> The agenda stores rule instances that are eligible to be executed. If the agenda is empty, the execution has no effect. Rule instances placed in the agenda are said to be eligible. Often, in the agenda, several rules are eligible. Consequently, the rule engine has to have some way of deciding which particular rule in the agenda should be executed. </p> <h3 id="negative-patterns">Negative Patterns</h3> <p>Negative Patterns are used for expressing the non-existence of a particular type of objects in the working memory. Generally, positive patterns are checked with the objects present in the working memory, By using these negative patterns in this algorithm we can reduce checking for all the patterns with the objects available.</p> <p>For specifying the negative patterns in the working memory, we should use <strong><em>“not”</em></strong> keyword prior to the condition of the objects.</p> <h3 id="object-notifications">Object Notifications</h3> <p>We have four statements to control the individual operations of the objects in the working memory. Operations include – Object insertion, Object removal, Object Update and Attribute modification.</p> <h3 id="reteplus-network-operation">RetePlus network operation</h3> <p class="p"> The RetePlus network indexes rules so as to minimize the number of rules and conditions that need to be evaluated whenever the working memory is changed. The network minimizes the number of evaluations by sharing tests between rules and propagating changes incrementally. When all the tests have been completed, the network designates a rule. </p> <p class="p"> A RetePlus network can be represented as a graph composed of three zones: </p> <p class="p"> <span style="text-decoration: underline;"><strong>Discrimination tree</strong></span> </p> <p class="p"> A discrimination tree is a pattern-matching process that performs tests. These tests are represented by diamond shapes at the top of the network. The tests concern the classes of objects and the values of their attributes. Input to this tree consists of tokens representing each of the current objects in the working memory. When the pattern deals with only one object and its attributes, it is said to be a discrimination test. When it is a combination, it is called a join; these appear in the lower part of the graph. </p> <p class="p"> <span style="text-decoration: underline;"><strong>Alpha nodes</strong></span> </p> <p class="p"> An alpha node is formed at the next level of the network, for each token that passes the tests of the discrimination tree. Each node is composed of one or several tokens, represented by round-cornered rectangles (there are three alpha nodes in the figure). One alpha node contains two B-class tokens. The other two nodes contain only one class token each—A-class and C-class tokens, respectively. </p> <p class="p"> <span style="text-decoration: underline;"><strong>Tests and tuples</strong></span> </p> <p class="p"> The third zone of the network matches tokens of several classes of objects. The resulting nodes are known as tuples, which will be made up of several tokens. The equality test between attributes a2 and b3 gives rise to a node composed of two pairs of tokens, and the test between attributes b2 and c1 then filters out a triplet of tokens. In a RetePlus network, we often refer to tuples of this kind as join nodes. </p> <h2 id="reteplus-execution-example">RetePlus Execution Example</h2> <h6 id="lets-imagine-that-there-are-two-rules-as-shown-below">Let’s imagine that there are two rules as shown below.</h6> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 480px)" srcset="/assets/img/blog/RetePlus-Example-480.webp"/> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 800px)" srcset="/assets/img/blog/RetePlus-Example-800.webp"/> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 1400px)" srcset="/assets/img/blog/RetePlus-Example-1400.webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/blog/RetePlus-Example.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="auto" height="auto" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> <h6 id="now-objects-are-loaded-into-the-working-memory">Now objects are loaded into the Working Memory.</h6> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 480px)" srcset="/assets/img/blog/Objects-are-loaded-into-Working-memory-480.webp"/> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 800px)" srcset="/assets/img/blog/Objects-are-loaded-into-Working-memory-800.webp"/> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 1400px)" srcset="/assets/img/blog/Objects-are-loaded-into-Working-memory-1400.webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/blog/Objects-are-loaded-into-Working-memory.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="auto" height="auto" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> <h6 id="now-pattern-matching-happens-and-if-rules-get-matched-with-the-objects-rule-instances-are-created-and-added-to-the-agenda">Now pattern matching happens and if rules get matched with the objects, rule instances are created and added to the agenda.</h6> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 480px)" srcset="/assets/img/blog/Agenda-gets-created-480.webp"/> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 800px)" srcset="/assets/img/blog/Agenda-gets-created-800.webp"/> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 1400px)" srcset="/assets/img/blog/Agenda-gets-created-1400.webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/blog/Agenda-gets-created.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="auto" height="auto" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> <h6 id="working-memory-objects-get-updated-with-new-values-that-got-fired-from-the-agenda">Working memory objects get updated with new values that got fired from the agenda.</h6> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 480px)" srcset="/assets/img/blog/Working-Memory-objects-get-updated-480.webp"/> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 800px)" srcset="/assets/img/blog/Working-Memory-objects-get-updated-800.webp"/> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 1400px)" srcset="/assets/img/blog/Working-Memory-objects-get-updated-1400.webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/blog/Working-Memory-objects-get-updated.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="auto" height="auto" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> <h6 id="rule-firing-continues">Rule firing continues.</h6> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 480px)" srcset="/assets/img/blog/Other-rules-in-agenda-continues-to-fire-480.webp"/> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 800px)" srcset="/assets/img/blog/Other-rules-in-agenda-continues-to-fire-800.webp"/> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 1400px)" srcset="/assets/img/blog/Other-rules-in-agenda-continues-to-fire-1400.webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/blog/Other-rules-in-agenda-continues-to-fire.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="auto" height="auto" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> <h6 id="in-the-end-when-no-rules-get-matched-with-the-working-memory-objects-rule-firing-stops">In the end, when no rules get matched with the Working memory objects, rule firing stops.</h6> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 480px)" srcset="/assets/img/blog/Agenda-and-Working-memory-in-the-end-480.webp"/> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 800px)" srcset="/assets/img/blog/Agenda-and-Working-memory-in-the-end-800.webp"/> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 1400px)" srcset="/assets/img/blog/Agenda-and-Working-memory-in-the-end-1400.webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/blog/Agenda-and-Working-memory-in-the-end.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="auto" height="auto" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> <h2 id="wrapping-up">Wrapping Up</h2> <p>Well, thats all about the RetePlus Algorithm! Feel free to comment your thoughts in the comments section below. Happy learning! Happy Exploring!!&lt;/li&gt; &lt;/ol&gt;</p> <h2 id="references">References</h2> <p><em><a href="https://www.ibm.com/support/knowledgecenter/SSQP76_8.5.1/com.ibm.odm.dserver.rules.designer.debug/optimizing_topics/tpc_opt_reteplusalgo.html">https://www.ibm.com/support/knowledgecenter/SSQP76_8.5.1/com.ibm.odm.dserver.rules.designer.debug/optimizing_topics/tpc_opt_reteplusalgo.html</a></em></p>]]></content><author><name>Bala Subramanyam Lanka</name></author><category term="Algorithms"/><category term="ODM"/><category term="reteplus-algorithm"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[RetePlus algorithm is one of the execution modes in IBM ODM which is based on Rete algorithm. It works based on working memory, agenda creation, supports negative patterns, object notification, and Logical Objects.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Synchronizing Rules and RuleDocs – Rule Solutions for Office, ODM</title><link href="https://thisisbalu.github.io/synchronising-rules-ruledocs-rule-solutions-office/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Synchronizing Rules and RuleDocs – Rule Solutions for Office, ODM"/><published>2016-06-02T20:25:15+00:00</published><updated>2016-06-02T20:25:15+00:00</updated><id>https://thisisbalu.github.io/synchronising-rules-ruledocs-rule-solutions-office</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://thisisbalu.github.io/synchronising-rules-ruledocs-rule-solutions-office/"><![CDATA[<h2 id="introduction">Introduction</h2> <p>RuleDocs are Microsoft Office documents that contain your rules, decision tables, and ruleflows. Rules and ruleflows are stored in Word documents, while decision tables are stored as spreadsheets in Excel. We use t to edit and manage rules offline. You can also use them to present the rules together with documentation and supporting information, including the original policy or requirement.</p> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 480px)" srcset="/assets/img/blog/rules-ruledocs-rule-solutions-office-ibm-odm-480.webp"/> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 800px)" srcset="/assets/img/blog/rules-ruledocs-rule-solutions-office-ibm-odm-800.webp"/> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 1400px)" srcset="/assets/img/blog/rules-ruledocs-rule-solutions-office-ibm-odm-1400.webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/blog/rules-ruledocs-rule-solutions-office-ibm-odm.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="auto" height="auto" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> <p>You can store your RuleDocs at a location that is accessible to multiple users. Other users can then open RuleDocs for editing without accessing the <span class="keyword">Decision Center</span> console.</p> <blockquote> <p>To use these docs to edit your rules, you must set file associations for <span class="ph filepath">.docx</span> and <span class="ph filepath">.xlsx</span> to Microsoft Office Word and Excel, not just with the Microsoft Word and Excel viewers.</p> </blockquote> <h2 id="decision-center---publish-and-update">Decision Center - Publish and Update</h2> <p>When you work with these Docs in this way, you publish and update them from <span class="keyword">Decision Center</span> to make sure that the rules in <span class="keyword">Decision Center</span> and those in your Docs remain synchronized.</p> <ol> <li><strong>Publish</strong>: To send the rules from Decision Center to RuleDocs on a file system.</li> <li><strong>Update</strong>: To save any changes made to your RuleDocs back to Decision Center</li> </ol> <p>When we download Rule Solutions for office, we will be able to see menu added to the Microsoft Word and Microsoft Excel. Rules menu will be added for Word and Decision Table Menu will be added to the Excel. Note that these menus can be seen only when the rules were published to the RuleDocs.<figure id="attachment_1424" aria-describedby="caption-attachment-1424" style="width: 840px" class="wp-caption aligncenter"></figure></p> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 480px)" srcset="/assets/img/blog/rule-solutions-for-office-1024x294-480.webp"/> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 800px)" srcset="/assets/img/blog/rule-solutions-for-office-1024x294-800.webp"/> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 1400px)" srcset="/assets/img/blog/rule-solutions-for-office-1024x294-1400.webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/blog/rule-solutions-for-office-1024x294.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="auto" height="auto" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> <p class="shortdesc"> <a href="http://www.balasubramanyamlanka.com/rule-solutions-office-installation-odm/"><span class="keyword">Rule Solutions for Office</span></a> supports different versions of Office. <span class="keyword">Rule Solutions for Office</span> works with Versions 2007 and 2010 of Microsoft Excel and Word. When you install <span class="keyword">Rule Solutions for Office</span>, you extend Excel and Word with add-ins that provide rule viewing, editing and management features for the RuleDocs. </p> <h2 id="publish-rules-to-ruledocs">Publish rules to Ruledocs:</h2> <h3 id="step-1">Step 1</h3> <p>Open Decision Center, Select your project. In this case project, name is MyFirstProject_rules</p> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 480px)" srcset="/assets/img/blog/Decision-Center-1024x621-480.webp"/> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 800px)" srcset="/assets/img/blog/Decision-Center-1024x621-800.webp"/> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 1400px)" srcset="/assets/img/blog/Decision-Center-1024x621-1400.webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/blog/Decision-Center-1024x621.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="auto" height="auto" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> <h3 id="step-2">Step 2</h3> <p>Go to the project tab in decision center and select Publish Rules to RuleDocs in Rule Solutions for Office Section.</p> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 480px)" srcset="/assets/img/blog/Decision-Center-Project-Tab-1024x628-480.webp"/> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 800px)" srcset="/assets/img/blog/Decision-Center-Project-Tab-1024x628-800.webp"/> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 1400px)" srcset="/assets/img/blog/Decision-Center-Project-Tab-1024x628-1400.webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/blog/Decision-Center-Project-Tab-1024x628.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="auto" height="auto" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> <h3 id="step-3">Step 3</h3> <p>Three sub steps here</p> <h4 id="step-13">Step 1/3</h4> <p>Specify the local destination folder in Publish rules to RuleDocs (1/3) and click on next. Here we specify where we want to publish the RuleDoc and then edit the RuleDocs. In the <strong><span class="ph uicontrol">Publication location</span></strong> field, select a location from the drop-down list. The Configuration Manager must have created the location beforehand. In the <strong><span class="ph uicontrol">Additional path</span></strong> field, add any required subfolders to this location.</p> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 480px)" srcset="/assets/img/blog/Publishing-rules-to-RuleDocs-1-1024x628-480.webp"/> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 800px)" srcset="/assets/img/blog/Publishing-rules-to-RuleDocs-1-1024x628-800.webp"/> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 1400px)" srcset="/assets/img/blog/Publishing-rules-to-RuleDocs-1-1024x628-1400.webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/blog/Publishing-rules-to-RuleDocs-1-1024x628.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="auto" height="auto" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> <h4 id="step-23">Step 2/3</h4> <p>Select the options for the RuleDocs in Publish rules to RuleDocs (2/3) and then click on next. Here, we specify which rules to include, how your RuleDoc is to be organized, and the locale. By default, all action rules, decision tables, and ruleflows of the current project are published to these Docs. However, you can select a subset based on an existing query. If you select a query when republishing to the same location, only rules selected by the query are published. This means that changes to rules in either <span class="keyword">Decision Center</span> or in the RuleDocs are taken into account if the query does not select those rules.</p> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 480px)" srcset="/assets/img/blog/Publishing-rules-to-RuleDocs-2-1024x629-480.webp"/> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 800px)" srcset="/assets/img/blog/Publishing-rules-to-RuleDocs-2-1024x629-800.webp"/> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 1400px)" srcset="/assets/img/blog/Publishing-rules-to-RuleDocs-2-1024x629-1400.webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/blog/Publishing-rules-to-RuleDocs-2-1024x629.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="auto" height="auto" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> <h4 id="step-33">Step 3/3</h4> <p>Specify the actions to take for each rule in Publish rules to RuleDocs (3/3) and then click next. At the start of this step, <span class="keyword">Decision Center</span> displays a table comparing the synchronization state between the rules in <span class="keyword">Decision Center</span> and the folder location to which you are publishing and proposes an action to take for each rule. For example, during an initial publish, no RuleDocs exist at the publication location, so all actions are <span class="ph uicontrol">Add rule in <span class="keyword">Rule Solutions for Office.</span></span></p> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 480px)" srcset="/assets/img/blog/Publishing-rules-to-RuleDocs-3-1024x630-480.webp"/> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 800px)" srcset="/assets/img/blog/Publishing-rules-to-RuleDocs-3-1024x630-800.webp"/> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 1400px)" srcset="/assets/img/blog/Publishing-rules-to-RuleDocs-3-1024x630-1400.webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/blog/Publishing-rules-to-RuleDocs-3-1024x630.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="auto" height="auto" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> <h3 id="step-4">Step 4</h3> <p>Publishing status</p> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 480px)" srcset="/assets/img/blog/Publishing-Status-1024x625-480.webp"/> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 800px)" srcset="/assets/img/blog/Publishing-Status-1024x625-800.webp"/> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 1400px)" srcset="/assets/img/blog/Publishing-Status-1024x625-1400.webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/blog/Publishing-Status-1024x625.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="auto" height="auto" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> <p>Now all the rules from the project will be converted into the RuleDocs and saved to the local computer destination provided while publishing.</p> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 480px)" srcset="/assets/img/blog/RuleDocs-saved-to-specified-local-destination-1024x681-480.webp"/> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 800px)" srcset="/assets/img/blog/RuleDocs-saved-to-specified-local-destination-1024x681-800.webp"/> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 1400px)" srcset="/assets/img/blog/RuleDocs-saved-to-specified-local-destination-1024x681-1400.webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/blog/RuleDocs-saved-to-specified-local-destination-1024x681.png" class=" img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="auto" height="auto" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> <p>Now all the rules from the decision center are converted into the Rule Docs and saved into our local system folder. We can now start working offline with the rules. We can Update them, add new entries in decision tables, delete some of the rules, modify the rule flow.<figure id="attachment_1452" aria-describedby="caption-attachment-1452" style="width: 840px" class="wp-caption aligncenter"></figure></p> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 480px)" srcset="/assets/img/blog/Decision-Table-in-Microsoft-Excel-xslx-1024x593-480.webp"/> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 800px)" srcset="/assets/img/blog/Decision-Table-in-Microsoft-Excel-xslx-1024x593-800.webp"/> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 1400px)" srcset="/assets/img/blog/Decision-Table-in-Microsoft-Excel-xslx-1024x593-1400.webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/blog/Decision-Table-in-Microsoft-Excel-xslx-1024x593.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="auto" height="auto" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> <p>All the changes that are done to these docs are saved locally in the specified location. Once we complete all our changes we can again update the decision center with all these changes. Let’s see how to Update the rules from the RuleDocs.</p> <h2 id="update-rules-from-ruledocs">Update rules from RuleDocs</h2> <p>Let’s assume that we have added some entries to the decision table of the project. For updating the rules with changes of RuleDocs in local:</p> <h3 id="step-1-1">Step 1</h3> <p>Open the Decision center, select our project on the home page then select project tab. Now select Update rules from RuleDocs in the Rule Solutions for Office section.</p> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 480px)" srcset="/assets/img/blog/Decision-Center-Project-Tab-1024x628-480.webp"/> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 800px)" srcset="/assets/img/blog/Decision-Center-Project-Tab-1024x628-800.webp"/> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 1400px)" srcset="/assets/img/blog/Decision-Center-Project-Tab-1024x628-1400.webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/blog/Decision-Center-Project-Tab-1024x628.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="auto" height="auto" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> <h3 id="step-2-1">Step 2</h3> <p>In the next page specify the local docs path for updating the rules in Update rules from RuleDocs (1/2) section and then click next.</p> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 480px)" srcset="/assets/img/blog/Update-rules-from-RuleDocs-12-1024x624-480.webp"/> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 800px)" srcset="/assets/img/blog/Update-rules-from-RuleDocs-12-1024x624-800.webp"/> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 1400px)" srcset="/assets/img/blog/Update-rules-from-RuleDocs-12-1024x624-1400.webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/blog/Update-rules-from-RuleDocs-12-1024x624.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="auto" height="auto" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> <h3 id="step-3-1">Step 3</h3> <p>Select the rules that should be updated into the rules from Update rules from RuleDocs (2/2) section and then click finish.</p> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 480px)" srcset="/assets/img/blog/Update-rules-from-RuleDocs-22-1024x626-480.webp"/> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 800px)" srcset="/assets/img/blog/Update-rules-from-RuleDocs-22-1024x626-800.webp"/> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 1400px)" srcset="/assets/img/blog/Update-rules-from-RuleDocs-22-1024x626-1400.webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/blog/Update-rules-from-RuleDocs-22-1024x626.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="auto" height="auto" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> <h3 id="step-4-1">Step 4</h3> <p>Updating progress.</p> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 480px)" srcset="/assets/img/blog/Updating-Progress-1024x635-480.webp"/> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 800px)" srcset="/assets/img/blog/Updating-Progress-1024x635-800.webp"/> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 1400px)" srcset="/assets/img/blog/Updating-Progress-1024x635-1400.webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/blog/Updating-Progress-1024x635.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="auto" height="auto" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> <h3 id="step-5">Step 5</h3> <p>Check your rule in explore tab in the decision center, Vola! It gets updated with the RuleDocs from the local.</p> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 480px)" srcset="/assets/img/blog/Decision-Table-gets-updated-in-the-Rules-1024x627-480.webp"/> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 800px)" srcset="/assets/img/blog/Decision-Table-gets-updated-in-the-Rules-1024x627-800.webp"/> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 1400px)" srcset="/assets/img/blog/Decision-Table-gets-updated-in-the-Rules-1024x627-1400.webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/blog/Decision-Table-gets-updated-in-the-Rules-1024x627.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="auto" height="auto" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> <h2 id="edit-rules-decision-tables-and-ruleflows">Edit Rules, Decision tables, and Ruleflows</h2> <p>Edit Rules, Decision tables, and Ruleflows without publishing and updating rules and docs. We can also use <span class="keyword">Rule Solutions for Office</span> for editing if you want to edit an element without publishing and updating. You can edit action rules, decision tables, and ruleflows.</p> <blockquote> <p>The Configuration Manager must activate the feature for the icons to appear in the rule tables</p> </blockquote> <h3 id="step-1-2">Step 1</h3> <p>On the Explore tab, click Edit this element in Rule Solutions for Office next to the name of the project element in the table (<img class="image" src="https://www.ibm.com/support/knowledgecenter/en/SSQP76_8.7.1/com.ibm.odm.dcenter.bu.econsole/images/icon_edit_word.jpg" alt="Edit in Word"/> for action rules and ruleflows, or <img class="image" src="https://www.ibm.com/support/knowledgecenter/en/SSQP76_8.7.1/com.ibm.odm.dcenter.bu.econsole/images/icon_edit_excel.jpg" alt="Edit in Excel"/> for decision tables).</p> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 480px)" srcset="/assets/img/blog/Edit-in-Rule-Solutions-for-Office-480.webp"/> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 800px)" srcset="/assets/img/blog/Edit-in-Rule-Solutions-for-Office-800.webp"/> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 1400px)" srcset="/assets/img/blog/Edit-in-Rule-Solutions-for-Office-1400.webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/blog/Edit-in-Rule-Solutions-for-Office.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="auto" height="auto" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> <h3 id="step-2-2">Step 2</h3> <p>In the File Download window, click <span class="ph uicontrol">Open</span></p> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 480px)" srcset="/assets/img/blog/Download-480.webp"/> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 800px)" srcset="/assets/img/blog/Download-800.webp"/> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 1400px)" srcset="/assets/img/blog/Download-1400.webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/blog/Download.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="auto" height="auto" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> <h3 id="step-3-2">Step 3</h3> <p>In the Rule Solutions for Office window, click OK. A RuleDoc containing the contents of the project element opens</p> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 480px)" srcset="/assets/img/blog/RuleDoc-opens-with-decisiontable-480.webp"/> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 800px)" srcset="/assets/img/blog/RuleDoc-opens-with-decisiontable-800.webp"/> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 1400px)" srcset="/assets/img/blog/RuleDoc-opens-with-decisiontable-1400.webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/blog/RuleDoc-opens-with-decisiontable.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="auto" height="auto" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> <h3 id="step-4-2">Step 4</h3> <p>Edit the project element in the RuleDoc. Click check in to commit your changes.</p> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 480px)" srcset="/assets/img/blog/Update-changes-and-click-check-into-commit-changes-480.webp"/> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 800px)" srcset="/assets/img/blog/Update-changes-and-click-check-into-commit-changes-800.webp"/> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 1400px)" srcset="/assets/img/blog/Update-changes-and-click-check-into-commit-changes-1400.webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/blog/Update-changes-and-click-check-into-commit-changes.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="auto" height="auto" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> <h3 id="step-5-1">Step 5</h3> <p>Decision Center Authentication for committing the changes.</p> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 480px)" srcset="/assets/img/blog/Decision-Center-Authentication-480.webp"/> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 800px)" srcset="/assets/img/blog/Decision-Center-Authentication-800.webp"/> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 1400px)" srcset="/assets/img/blog/Decision-Center-Authentication-1400.webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/blog/Decision-Center-Authentication.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="auto" height="auto" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> <h3 id="step-6">Step 6</h3> <p>Enter the Commit Documentation before checking in the code into the repository. &lt;p&gt;</p> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 480px)" srcset="/assets/img/blog/Commit-Documentaion-for-rule-480.webp"/> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 800px)" srcset="/assets/img/blog/Commit-Documentaion-for-rule-800.webp"/> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 1400px)" srcset="/assets/img/blog/Commit-Documentaion-for-rule-1400.webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/blog/Commit-Documentaion-for-rule.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="auto" height="auto" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> <h3 id="step-7">Step 7</h3> <p>Open the Explore tab in the decision center to check the rule! Yes, the rule gets updated immediately after the commit from Rule Solutions for Office.</p> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 480px)" srcset="/assets/img/blog/Rule-gets-updated-480.webp"/> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 800px)" srcset="/assets/img/blog/Rule-gets-updated-800.webp"/> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 1400px)" srcset="/assets/img/blog/Rule-gets-updated-1400.webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/blog/Rule-gets-updated.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="auto" height="auto" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> <h2 id="wrapping-up">Wrapping Up</h2> <p>Well! I guess that is a very big post about the Rule Solutions for Office and the Docs. I had to make sure that all the information posted here is simple and easily understandable. Feel free to express your ideas or new points in the comments section below. Happy Learning! Happy Exploring!!&lt;/li&gt; &lt;/ol&gt;</p> <h2 id="references">References</h2> <ol> <li><a href="https://www.ibm.com/support/knowledgecenter">https://www.ibm.com/support/knowledgecenter</a></li> <li><a href="https://blogs.perficient.com">https://blogs.perficient.com</a></li> </ol>]]></content><author><name>Bala Subramanyam Lanka</name></author><category term="IBM"/><category term="ODM"/><category term="ruledocs"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[RuleDocs are Microsoft Office documents that contain your rules, decision tables, and ruleflows. Rules and ruleflows are stored in Word documents, while decision tables are stored as spreadsheets in Excel.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Rule Solutions for Office Installation – IBM ODM</title><link href="https://thisisbalu.github.io/rule-solutions-office-installation-odm/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Rule Solutions for Office Installation – IBM ODM"/><published>2016-05-31T17:59:20+00:00</published><updated>2016-05-31T17:59:20+00:00</updated><id>https://thisisbalu.github.io/rule-solutions-office-installation-odm</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://thisisbalu.github.io/rule-solutions-office-installation-odm/"><![CDATA[<p class="p"> <span class="keyword">Rule Solutions for Office</span> enables you to edit business rules in Microsoft Office documents called RuleDocs. You can update and share rules with RuleDocs, which can also provide supporting documentation and information such as the original policies for the rules. <span class="keyword">Rule Solutions </span>works in conjunction with <span class="keyword">Decision Center</span>, which serves as a workspace for business users to collaborate on authoring, editing, organizing, and searching for business rules. </p> <h2 id="what-is-rule-solutions-for-office">What is Rule Solutions for Office?</h2> <li class="p"> Rule Solutions are mainly introduced for the Business users. Rules can be easily modified and maintained by business users. </li> <li class="p"> Rule Solutions for Office enables you to edit business rules in Microsoft Office documents called RuleDocs. You can update and share rules with RuleDocs, which can also provide supporting documentation and information such as the original policies for the rules. </li> <li class="p"> Rule Solutions for Office works in conjunction with Decision Center, which serves as a workspace for business users to collaborate on authoring, editing, organizing, and searching for business rules. </li> <li class="p"> Decision Center publishes action rules and ruleflows as Microsoft Word RuleDocs. Rule Solutions for Office editors integrated with Word let you edit the rules and ruleflows using a natural language syntax. These editors help you use correct business vocabulary and rule syntax through the Intellirule Editor, which is also used in Decision Center. <p> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 480px)" srcset="/assets/img/blog/rule-solutions-for-office-ibm-odm-480.webp"/> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 800px)" srcset="/assets/img/blog/rule-solutions-for-office-ibm-odm-800.webp"/> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 1400px)" srcset="/assets/img/blog/rule-solutions-for-office-ibm-odm-1400.webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/blog/rule-solutions-for-office-ibm-odm.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="auto" height="auto" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> <li class="p"> Decision Center publishes rule decision tables to Microsoft Excel RuleDocs. The Rule Solutions decision table editor in Excel enables you to view and edit sets of similar action rules. You can also use Excel commands to change table properties. </li> <li class="p"> You use Rule Solutions for Office and RuleDocs to view, review and edit rules offline. You can also share RuleDocs by email or through a common server to collaborate on their contents with people inside or outside your organization. </li> <li class="p"> You can also open a rule directly inside Decision Center to edit it in Rule Solutions without publishing and synchronizing a RuleDoc. When a rule is checked out this way, Decision Center locks it to prevent modification conflicts. No one else can change the rule until it has been checked back in. </li> <li class="p"> <p class="p"> <span class="keyword">Rule Solutions</span> synchronizes the changes made to a RuleDoc back to the environment from which the RuleDoc was published. Even if you change the organization of RuleDocs in a folder or move rules from one RuleDoc to another, your RuleDocs still sync back to their source. </p> </li>&lt;/ol&gt; <h2> Installing Rule Solutions for Office </h2> <ol> <li> Once the installation of Decision Center is complete, you can manually run the installer for Rule Solutions. </li> <li> If you installed the product with <span class="keyword">Installation Manager</span>, make sure that you selected the <span class="ph uicontrol"><span class="keyword">Rule Solutions for Office</span></span> feature. </li> <li> Navigate to <InstallDir>/Rule Solutions for Office/ &lt;/li&gt; <li> Double-click the RuleSolutionsForOffice.exe file to run it. </li> <li> Follow the steps in the installation wizard. </li> &lt;/ol&gt; <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 480px)" srcset="/assets/img/blog/rule-solutions-for-office-480.webp"/> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 800px)" srcset="/assets/img/blog/rule-solutions-for-office-800.webp"/> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 1400px)" srcset="/assets/img/blog/rule-solutions-for-office-1400.webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/blog/rule-solutions-for-office.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="auto" height="auto" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> <blockquote> <div class="section context"> <span class="keyword">Rule Solutions for Office</span> is an optional component that provides a way for business users to create and edit business rules in Microsoft Word or Excel. The <span class="ph uicontrol"><span class="keyword">Rule Solutions for Office</span></span> feature in <span class="keyword">Installation Manager</span> copies the installer for <span class="keyword">Rule Solutions for Office</span> to your installation directory. </div> </blockquote> <div class="section context"> Happy Learning! Happy Exploring!! </div> <div class="section context"> </div> </InstallDir></li></ol></p></li>]]></content><author><name>Bala Subramanyam Lanka</name></author><category term="IBM"/><category term="ODM"/><category term="odm"/><category term="brms"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Rule Solutions for Office enables you to edit business rules in Microsoft Office documents called RuleDocs. You can update and share rules with RuleDocs, which can also provide supporting documentation and information such as the original policies for the rules.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Organizing your application into rule projects – IBM ODM</title><link href="https://thisisbalu.github.io/organizing-application-rule-projects-ibm-odm/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Organizing your application into rule projects – IBM ODM"/><published>2016-05-26T01:48:58+00:00</published><updated>2016-05-26T01:48:58+00:00</updated><id>https://thisisbalu.github.io/organizing-application-rule-projects-ibm-odm</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://thisisbalu.github.io/organizing-application-rule-projects-ibm-odm/"><![CDATA[<p>By organizing your rule application as modular rule projects, you can improve the performance of Rule Designer for large rule applications, and facilitate the assignment of permissions in Decision Center</p> <h2 id="organizing-business-rules-into-rule-projects">Organizing business rules into rule projects</h2> <p>In Rule Designer, many operations are carried out at the rule project level, such as build, queries, refactoring, and ruleset extraction. Other operations, such as Content Assist and debugging, require browsing through all the rule project items. If you have a large number of business rules in your rule project, these operations become slower. The following diagram shows one rule project with two sets of business rules, Set A, and Set B.<figure id="attachment_1410" aria-describedby="caption-attachment-1410" style="width: 167px" class="wp-caption aligncenter"></figure></p> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 480px)" srcset="/assets/img/blog/rule-projects-480.webp"/> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 800px)" srcset="/assets/img/blog/rule-projects-800.webp"/> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 1400px)" srcset="/assets/img/blog/rule-projects-1400.webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/blog/rule-projects.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="auto" height="auto" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> <p>To avoid having to manage a large number of rule artifacts in your projects, you can try to break down your application into several rule projects. These rule projects must then reference each other. The following diagram demonstrates this modular organization. Here, you work with the Set A business rule artifacts separately from the Set B business rule artifacts as they are in separate rule projects.<figure id="attachment_1411" aria-describedby="caption-attachment-1411" style="width: 391px" class="wp-caption aligncenter"></figure></p> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 480px)" srcset="/assets/img/blog/breaking-down-rule-project-480.webp"/> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 800px)" srcset="/assets/img/blog/breaking-down-rule-project-800.webp"/> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 1400px)" srcset="/assets/img/blog/breaking-down-rule-project-1400.webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/blog/breaking-down-rule-project.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="auto" height="auto" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> <h2 id="organizing-rule-projects-based-on-decision-center-permissions">Organizing rule projects based on Decision Center permissions</h2> <p>In the Decision Center console, you can define permissions at the rule project level while defining permissions at the rule package level requires you to specify the permissions programmatically. Therefore, if you organize your rule projects according to how you plan to define permissions, you do not need to define these permissions programmatically.</p> <p>By default, in Decision Center, queries, branches, and extractors only cover the current project. However, you can modify this behavior in the Decision Center console to include referenced rule projects. Deployment baselines include all referenced projects that are necessary for deployment.</p> <h2 id="organizing-the-bom-into-rule-projects">Organizing the BOM into rule projects</h2> <p>If a set of rules uses only a part of the business object model, you can consider isolating this set of rules and the part of the business object model into a separate rule project. Then, when you work with the rules, you have visibility only on the required BOM classes.</p> <p>You can also split a large BOM entry into several smaller ones for more flexibility, as illustrated in the following figure.<figure id="attachment_1413" aria-describedby="caption-attachment-1413" style="width: 576px" class="wp-caption aligncenter"></figure></p> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 480px)" srcset="/assets/img/blog/breaking-down-bom-entries-480.webp"/> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 800px)" srcset="/assets/img/blog/breaking-down-bom-entries-800.webp"/> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 1400px)" srcset="/assets/img/blog/breaking-down-bom-entries-1400.webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/blog/breaking-down-bom-entries.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="auto" height="auto" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> <p>When you work with a very large business object model, the completion menus in the Intellirule and Guided editors can become quite large. The size can both be usability and a performance issue. To reduce the number of completion entries, and to make them more relevant to your rules, use categories. Categories are a good way to organize your vocabulary into subsets.<figure id="attachment_1414" aria-describedby="caption-attachment-1414" style="width: 457px" class="wp-caption aligncenter"></figure></p> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 480px)" srcset="/assets/img/blog/diamond-shaped-organization-480.webp"/> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 800px)" srcset="/assets/img/blog/diamond-shaped-organization-800.webp"/> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 1400px)" srcset="/assets/img/blog/diamond-shaped-organization-1400.webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/blog/diamond-shaped-organization.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="auto" height="auto" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> <p>If you decide to use a diamond-shaped organization, as illustrated in the figure above, with a rule project that defines a ruleflow and references child rule projects, which share a single rule project for the BOM, make sure you define ruleset parameters in the rule project that contains the BOM. Be aware that if you define the same ruleset parameters in the child rule projects, these parameters appear as duplicates in the parent project.</p> <p>Happy learning! Happy Exploring!!</p> <p> </p> <p><em><strong>Sources</strong>:</em></p> <ul> <li><em><a href="https://www.ibm.com/support/knowledgecenter/SSQP76_8.5.1/com.ibm.odm.dserver.rules.designer.dev/developing_topics/tpc_rulep_org_into_ruleproj.html">https://www.ibm.com/support/knowledgecenter/SSQP76_8.5.1/com.ibm.odm.dserver.rules.designer.dev/developing_topics/tpc_rulep_org_into_ruleproj.html</a></em></li> </ul>]]></content><author><name>Bala Subramanyam Lanka</name></author><category term="ODM"/><category term="rule-projects"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[By organizing your rule application as modular rule projects, you can improve the performance of Rule Designer for large rule applications, and facilitate the assignment of permissions in Decision Center]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Development Standards for Execution Object Model (XOM)</title><link href="https://thisisbalu.github.io/development-standards-execution-object-model-xom/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Development Standards for Execution Object Model (XOM)"/><published>2016-05-24T19:48:17+00:00</published><updated>2016-05-24T19:48:17+00:00</updated><id>https://thisisbalu.github.io/development-standards-execution-object-model-xom</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://thisisbalu.github.io/development-standards-execution-object-model-xom/"><![CDATA[<p>The Execution Object Model (XOM) is the model against which the rules run. It references the application objects and data and is the base implementation of the Business Object Model (BOM). Rule projects reference the XOM. Through the Execution Object Model, the rule engine can access application objects and methods, which can be Java objects, XML data, or data from other sources. At run time, rules that were written against the BOM are run against the XOM.</p> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 480px)" srcset="/assets/img/blog/Execution-Object-Model-XOM-480.webp"/> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 800px)" srcset="/assets/img/blog/Execution-Object-Model-XOM-800.webp"/> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 1400px)" srcset="/assets/img/blog/Execution-Object-Model-XOM-1400.webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/blog/Execution-Object-Model-XOM.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="auto" height="auto" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> <p>Every BOM element (business element) must have a corresponding Execution Object Model element (execution element). The correspondence between execution elements and business elements does not need to be one-to-one. If a business element originates from an execution element, you do not need to specify an explicit mapping. If a business element does not originate from an execution element, you must specify a BOM to XOM mapping.</p> <p>When the data model is in Java, the BOM can directly be generated from Java Execution Object Model (XOM). XOM annotations are used to configure BOM generation and are also considered a standard way of documenting the BOM verbalizations in XOM. If you want to extend the BOM with business classes and methods, you can then map these business elements to XOM elements using BOM to XOM mapping in the BOM Editor.</p> <h2 id="annotations-to-the-xom">Annotations to the XOM</h2> <ul> <li>Annotations are added to the XOM to customize the way that the BOM is created from Java classes.</li> <li>You can use annotations in your Java source code. Annotations are a type of metadata that you can add to classes, members, and parameters.</li> <li>You use the annotations to apply changes to classes, members, or parameters in the BOM.</li> </ul> <p>For example, you can add an annotation to a class to define a business name for the class. In the BOM, the class takes the name defined by the annotation. When you create the BOM from the XOM, the BOM Verbalization page of the New BOM Entry wizard displays the business name of the class.</p> <p>There are eight different types of annotations those are provided by ilog.rules.bom.annotations package. They are as follows</p> <li> BoundedIntDomain </li> <li> BusinessName </li> <li> BusinessType </li> <li> CollectionDomain </li> <li> CustomProperties </li> <li> CustomProperty </li> <li> NotBusiness </li> <li> PatternDomain </li> <blockquote> <p>To use the annotations from the ilog.rules.bom.annotations package, you must add /studio/lib/jrules-engine.jar to the classpath of your XOM. However, if you just want to use the @java.beans.ConstructorProperties annotation, you do not need to add the jrules-engine.jar to the classpath.</p> </blockquote> <h2 id="notbusiness">@NotBusiness</h2> <p>The classes and members with the @NotBusiness annotation are not imported in the BOM. For example, if you encounter problems when loading a class, you can filter out the member that uses this class by setting the @NotBusiness annotation to this member.</p> <p><strong>Syntax</strong> : @NotBusines</p> <pre class="lang:default highlight:0 decode:true" title="In the XOM, the annotation can be used as follows">public class Customer {
 public Customer(String name) {...}
 public String getName() {...}
@NotBusiness
public Object readResolve() throws ObjectStreamException {...}
}</pre> <pre class="lang:default highlight:0 decode:true " title="The result in the BOM is the following code">class Customer {
 Customer(string arg);
 readonly string name;
}</pre> <h2 id="businessname">@BusinessName</h2> <p>In Java, the parameter names are not stored in the class. You can set the @BusinessName annotation to give a business name to the parameter. The parameter names are stored in the BOM and used in the BOM to XOM mapping, and in the DVS constructor for testing. Syntax @BusinessName(</p> <p>In Java, the parameter names are not stored in the class. You can set the @BusinessName annotation to give a business name to the parameter. The parameter names are stored in the BOM and used in the BOM to XOM mapping, and in the DVS constructor for testing.</p> <p><strong>Syntax</strong> : @BusinessName(<a string="">)</a></p> <pre class="lang:default highlight:0 decode:true" title="In the XOM, the annotation can be used as follows">public class Customer {
 public Customer(@BusinessName("name") String name) {...}
 public String getName() {...}
}</pre> <pre class="lang:default highlight:0 decode:true" title="The result in the BOM is the following code">class Customer {
 Customer(string name);
 readonly string name;
}</pre> <h2 id="businesstype">@BusinessType</h2> <p>The @BusinessType annotation changes the type of a member or a parameter in the BOM. For example, if you want to change a type int to an enumeration in the BOM to verbalize it. An enumeration is a class with a domain set as an enumeration of static references. When you apply the @BusinessType annotation to a method, the return type of the method is modified.</p> <p><strong>Syntax</strong> : @BusinessType(<a string="">)</a></p> <pre class="lang:default highlight:0 decode:true" title="In the XOM, the annotation can be used as follows">public class Customer {
 public Customer(@BusinessType("Category") int category) {...}
}</pre> <pre class="lang:default highlight:0 decode:true " title="The result in the BOM is the following code">class Customer {
 Customer(Category category);
}</pre> <h2 id="boundedintdomain">@BoundedIntDomain</h2> <p>The @BoundedIntDomain provides a bounded domain to specify an interval between two bounding values on a member or a parameter of type int.</p> <p><strong>Syntax</strong> : @BoundedIntDomain(min = <an int="">, max = <an int="">)</an></an></p> <pre class="lang:default highlight:0 decode:true " title="In the XOM, the annotation can be used as follows">public class Customer {
 @BoundedIntDomain(min = 0, max = 120)
 public int age;
}</pre> <pre class="lang:default highlight:0 decode:true " title="The result in the BOM is the following code">class Customer {
 int age domain [0,120];
}</pre> <h2 id="collectiondomain">@CollectionDomain</h2> <p>The @CollectionDomain provides a collection domain to specify the type of collection elements and the cardinality. The collection domain and the element type are used by the Business Action Language (BAL).</p> <p><strong>Syntax</strong> : @CollectionDomain(&lt;&gt;)</p> <pre class="lang:default highlight:0 decode:true " title=" In the XOM, the annotation can be used as follows">public class Cart {
@CollectionDomain(elementType = "Item")
public List items;
@CollectionDomain(min = 1, max = 12)
public Person[] passengers;
}</pre> <pre class="lang:default highlight:0 decode:true " title="The result in the BOM is the following code">class Cart{
List items domain 0,* class Item;
Person[] passengers domain 1,12 class Person;
}</pre> <h2 id="patterndomain">@PatternDomain</h2> <p>The @PatternDomain annotation enables you to specify a pattern domain for a member or a parameter.</p> <p><strong>Syntax</strong> : @PatternDomain(<a string="">)</a></p> <pre class="lang:default highlight:0 decode:true" title=" In the XOM, the annotation can be used as follows">public class Customer {
 @PatternDomain("[A-Za-z]");
 public String getName() {...}
}</pre> <pre class="lang:default highlight:0 decode:true " title="The result in the BOM is the following code">class Customer {
 readonly string name domain "[A-Za-z]";
}</pre> <h2 id="customproperty">@CustomProperty</h2> <p>The @CustomProperty annotation sets a property on a class, a member, or a parameter.</p> <p><strong>Syntax</strong> : @CustomProperty(name=<a string="">, value=<a string="">)</a></a></p> <pre class="lang:default highlight:0 decode:true " title=" In the XOM, the annotation can be used as follows">public class Customer {
 @CustomProperty(name = "dataio.default", value = "true")
 public Customer(@BusinessName("name") String name);
 public String getName() {...}
}</pre> <pre class="lang:default highlight:0 decode:true " title="The result in the BOM is the following code">class Customer {
 Customer(string name)
 property dataio.default "true";
 readonly string name;
}</pre> <h2 id="customproperties">@CustomProperties</h2> <p>The @CustomProperties annotation sets several properties on a class, a member, or a parameter.</p> <p><strong>Syntax</strong> @CustomProperties(names={<strings>},values={<strings>})</strings></strings></p> <pre class="lang:default highlight:0 decode:true " title="In the XOM, the annotation can be used as follows">public class Customer {
 @CustomProperties(names = {"cobol_length", "other" }, values = { "9",
"true"})
 public String getName() {...}
}</pre> <pre class="lang:default highlight:0 decode:true " title="The result in the BOM is the following code">class Customer {
 Customer(string name)
 property cobol_length "9"
 property other "true";
 readonly string name;
}</pre> <h2 id="javabeansconstructorproperties">@java.beans.ConstructorProperties</h2> <p>You can use the @java.beans.ConstructorProperties annotation to provide a name for a constructor. You can also use the@BusinessName on the parameters to give a name to each argument in the BOM.</p> <p><strong>Syntax</strong> : @java.beans.ConstructorProperties({<strings>})</strings></p> <pre class="lang:default highlight:0 decode:true " title="In the XOM, the annotation can be used as follows">public class Customer {
 @ConstructorProperties("name", "age")
 public Customer(String name, int age);
}</pre> <pre class="lang:default highlight:0 decode:true " title="The result in the BOM is the following code">class Customer {
 Customer(string name, int age);
}</pre> <p>Happy Learning! Happy Exploring!!</p> <p> </p> <p><em><strong><span style="text-decoration: underline;">Sources</span></strong>:</em></p> <ul> <li><em><a href="http://www.ibm.com/support/knowledgecenter">http://www.ibm.com/support/knowledgecenter</a></em></li> <li><em><a href="http://www.ibm.com/support/knowledgecenter/SSQP76_8.0.0/com.ibm.wodm.dserver.rules.ref.res/html/api/html/ilog/rules/bom/annotations/package-summary.html">http://www.ibm.com/support/knowledgecenter/SSQP76_8.0.0/com.ibm.wodm.dserver.rules.ref.res/html/api/html/ilog/rules/bom/annotations/package-summary.html</a></em></li> <li><em><a href="https://www.ibm.com/support/knowledgecenter/SSQP76_8.6.0/com.ibm.odm.dserver.rules.ref.res/html/api/html/ilog/rules/bom/annotations/package-summary.html">https://www.ibm.com/support/knowledgecenter/SSQP76_8.6.0/com.ibm.odm.dserver.rules.ref.res/html/api/html/ilog/rules/bom/annotations/package-summary.html</a></em></li> </ul>]]></content><author><name>Bala Subramanyam Lanka</name></author><category term="IBM"/><category term="ODM"/><category term="Annotations"/><category term="BOM"/><category term="XOM"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[The Execution Object Model (XOM) is the model against which the rules run. It references the application objects and data and is the base implementation of the Business Object Model (BOM). Rule projects reference the XOM.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">What is an Expert System?</title><link href="https://thisisbalu.github.io/expert-system/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="What is an Expert System?"/><published>2016-05-22T19:39:56+00:00</published><updated>2016-05-22T19:39:56+00:00</updated><id>https://thisisbalu.github.io/expert-system</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://thisisbalu.github.io/expert-system/"><![CDATA[<p>An Expert system is a computer system that uses artificial intelligence methods to solve problems within a specialized domain that ordinarily requires human expertise. They are designed to solve complex problems by reasoning about knowledge, represented primarily as if–then rules rather than through conventional procedural code.</p> <h2 id="how-expert-system-got-started">How Expert System got started?</h2> <p>The first system was developed in 1965 by Edward Feigenbaum and Joshua Lederberg of Stanford University in California, U.S. Dendral(an influential pioneer project in artificial intelligence of the 1960s. Its primary aim was to study hypothesis formation and discovery in science.), as their expert system was later known, was designed to analyze chemical compounds.<figure id="attachment_1391" aria-describedby="caption-attachment-1391" style="width: 308px" class="wp-caption aligncenter"></figure></p> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 480px)" srcset="/assets/img/blog/list-expert-system-480.webp"/> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 800px)" srcset="/assets/img/blog/list-expert-system-800.webp"/> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 1400px)" srcset="/assets/img/blog/list-expert-system-1400.webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/blog/list-expert-system.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="auto" height="auto" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> <h2 id="how-do-expert-systems-work">How Do Expert Systems Work?</h2> <p>An expert system has three main components.<figure id="attachment_1386" aria-describedby="caption-attachment-1386" style="width: 635px" class="wp-caption aligncenter"></figure></p> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 480px)" srcset="/assets/img/blog/expert-system-480.webp"/> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 800px)" srcset="/assets/img/blog/expert-system-800.webp"/> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 1400px)" srcset="/assets/img/blog/expert-system-1400.webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/blog/expert-system.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="auto" height="auto" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> <h3 id="knowledge-base">Knowledge Base</h3> <p>This is a <strong>collection of facts and rules</strong>. The knowledge base is created from <strong>information</strong> provided by **human experts. **It stores complex structured and unstructured information used by a computer system.</p> <h3 id="inference-engine">Inference Engine</h3> <p>An inference engine interprets and evaluates the facts in the knowledge base in order to provide an answer. The inference engine applies logical rules to the knowledge base and deducts new knowledge. This process would iterate as each new fact in the knowledge base could trigger additional rules in the inference engine.</p> <p>Inference engines work primarily in one of two modes called as forward chaining and backward chaining.</p> <ul> <li><strong>Forward chaining</strong> starts with the known facts and asserts new facts.</li> <li><strong>Backward chaining</strong> starts with goals and works backward to determine what facts must be asserted so that the goals can be achieved.</li> </ul> <h2 id="user-interface">User Interface</h2> <p>UI is the system that allows a <strong>non-expert user</strong> to <strong>query</strong> (question) the expert system, and to <strong>receive advice</strong>. The user-interface is designed to be a <strong>simple</strong> to use as possible.</p> <blockquote> <p>Inshort, the non-expert user queries the expert system by asking a question, or by answering questions asked by the expert system in <span style="text-decoration: underline;"><strong>user interface</strong></span>. The <span style="text-decoration: underline;"><strong>inference engine</strong></span> uses the query to search the <span style="text-decoration: underline;"><strong>knowledge base</strong></span> and then provides an answer or some advice to the user.</p> </blockquote> <h2 id="applications-of-expert-system">Applications of Expert System</h2> <p>According to the book <em><strong>Building expert systems</strong></em> written by _**‎Hayes-Roth, **_Expert Systems are divided into ten categories as follows.</p> <ol> <li><strong>Interpretation</strong> : Inferring situation descriptions from sensor data like speech detection.</li> <li><strong>Prediction</strong> : Inferring likely consequences of given situations like Preterm Birth Risk Assessment.</li> <li><strong>Diagnosis</strong> : Inferring system malfunctions from observables like CADUCEUS, MYCIN, PUFF, Mistral etc.,</li> <li><strong>Design</strong> : Configuring objects under constraints like Dendral, Mortgage Loan Advisor, R1 etc.,</li> <li><strong>Planning</strong> : Designing actions like Mission Planning for Autonomous Underwater Vehicle.</li> <li><strong>Monitoring</strong> : Comparing observations to plan vulnerabilities like REACTOR.</li> <li><strong>Debugging</strong> : Providing incremental solutions for complex problems like SAINT, MATHLAB, MACSYMA.</li> <li><strong>Repair</strong> : Executing a plan to administer a prescribed remedy like Toxic Spill Crisis Management.</li> <li><strong>Instruction</strong> : Diagnosing, assessing, and repairing student behavior like SMH.PAL, Intelligent Clinical Training, STEAMER.</li> <li><strong>Control</strong> : Interpreting, predicting, repairing, and monitoring system behaviors like Real Time Process Control, Space Shuttle Mission Control etc.,</li> </ol> <h2 id="want-to-try-expert-system-by-yourself">Want to try Expert System by yourself?</h2> <p>If you want to experience expert system yourself, you can try them some of the Health care expert systems out there in the internet.</p> <ol> <li><a href="http://www.nhs24.com/selfhelpguide/bodymap/">NHS24</a>, Scotland’s Health Expert system</li> <li><a href="http://www.questionmyhealth.com/">QuestionMyHealth</a>, is a nutrition expert system.</li> <li><a href="http://www.easydiagnosis.com/">EasyDiagnosis</a>, is also a Health Expert System. I guess this one is a paid service.</li> </ol> <p>All the information I have posted here is collected from the different websites and encyclopedias. Please find all the references in the sources section which will be listed below. Happy Learning! Happy Exploring!!</p> <p> </p> <p><em><strong>Sources</strong>:</em></p> <ul> <li><em><a href="http://www.igcseict.info/theory/7_2/expert/">http://www.igcseict.info/theory/7_2/expert/</a></em></li> <li><em><a href="http://www.britannica.com/technology/expert-system">http://www.britannica.com/technology/expert-system</a></em></li> <li><em><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/">https://en.wikipedia.org/</a></em></li> </ul>]]></content><author><name>Bala Subramanyam Lanka</name></author><category term="Expert System"/><category term="ai"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[An Expert system is a computer system that uses artificial intelligence methods to solve problems within a specialized domain that ordinarily requires human expertise.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">firing and firinglimit in Rule task – IBM ODM</title><link href="https://thisisbalu.github.io/firing-firinglimit-ruletask-ibm-odm/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="firing and firinglimit in Rule task – IBM ODM"/><published>2016-05-20T20:08:14+00:00</published><updated>2016-05-20T20:08:14+00:00</updated><id>https://thisisbalu.github.io/firing-firinglimit-ruletask-ibm-odm</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://thisisbalu.github.io/firing-firinglimit-ruletask-ibm-odm/"><![CDATA[<p>Configuring the Rule task execution plays the key role in executing the rules in a rule flow. firing and firinglimit are the two rule task properties that help rule execution in a rule flow.</p> <h2 id="firing-keyword">firing keyword</h2> <p class="shortdesc"> The firing keyword determines whether all the rules are executed. This keyword is used to determine whether all the rules of a rule task are executed or only one of them. </p> <h3 id="syntax">Syntax</h3> <pre class="toolbar:0 lang:default decode:true">
ruletask ruleTaskName 
{
   [firing = allrules|rule;] 
};
</pre> <blockquote> <div class="section"> All instances of one rule are executed. If only one rule is executed, use the keyword firinglimit. </div> </blockquote> <h2 id="firinglimit">firinglimit</h2> <p class="shortdesc"> The firinglimit keyword specifies the number of rules to be executed. The purpose of a rule task is to execute rules. You can modify the execution order and the number of rules that are executed. The keyword firinglimit specifies how many rules are executed. </p> <h3 id="syntax-1">Syntax</h3> <pre class="toolbar:0 lang:default decode:true ">ruletask ruleTaskName 
{
   [firinglimit = integer value;] 
};</pre> <p>It is good to have knowledge about these two properties to orchestrate the rules properly in the Operation Decision Management. It all depends on the orchestrator who designs the ruleflow. Happy Learning! Happy Exploring!!</p>]]></content><author><name>Bala Subramanyam Lanka</name></author><category term="ODM"/><category term="firing"/><category term="firing-limit"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Configuring the Rule task execution plays the key role in executing the rules in a rule flow. firing and firinglimit are the two rule task properties that help rule execution in a rule flow.]]></summary></entry></feed>